Guide to the John Shelton Curtiss papers, 1796-1981 UA.29.02.0158
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Shelton Curtiss papers
1796-1981
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Curtiss, John Shelton
UA.29.02.0158
6.5 Linear Feet
John Shelton Curtiss was a professor emeritus of history at Duke University, specializing in Russian history and civilization. The collection includes professional and personal papers, as well as extensive documentation of Curtiss family history and genealogy.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The John Curtiss papers were received by the Duke University Archives as a gift in June and September, 1981.
Collection Overview
The collection is divided into three series: professional papers, personal papers, and family history and genealogy.
Curtiss' professional papers are exclusively from after his retirement as a faculty member at Duke University. They include drafts of scholarly articles written by him after his retirement, book reviews and publication information for his book Russia's Crimean War, a C.V., and recommendations for former students.
His personal papers are much more extensive, covering the breadth of his activities during his retirement. Included is his work with a number of local organizations, such as the Durham County Public Library, the Kiwanis Club, the Ruritan society, and the Lebanon Volunteer Fire Department. Also included are personal correspondence, both with family and acquaintances, letters to congress, political activism, documents pertaining to land he partly owned in Texas, and an autobiography he wrote concerning his life in retirement.
The final series is materials pertaining to Curtiss family history and genealogy. These include family trees, baptismal and marriage certificates, correspondence dating back to the early 19th century between various distant relations, and a number of materials which appear to have belonged to his father, Harlow C. Curtiss. Photographs of many family members are present. Also included are photographs of a trip to Moscow John and Edna Curtiss took in 1955. The bulk of the material concerns the Curtiss' line, but some materials concerning the family history of Edna Sutter Curtiss are also included. Most material is manuscript, but at the end of the series are a number of bound volumes concerning family history in Connecticut and New England, as well as a copy of the complete works of Turgenev written in Russian.
Historical note
John Shelton Curtiss was a professor emeritus of history at Duke University. He was born on July 15th, 1899 to Harlow Clarke Curtiss, a prominent Buffalo New York attorney, and Ethel Mann Curtiss, his wife. John Curtiss attended Princeton University, graduating in 1921, and was a member of the undefeated Princeton Crew team.
Curtiss attended Columbia University for graduate school beginning in 1925. He taught at Brooklyn College from 1933-1936, as well as at Columbia from 1934-1936. He taught himself Russian as a graduate student, and began specializing in Russian history. Over his long career he made several trips to the Soviet Union for research and study.
Upon receiving his Ph.D. from Columbia in 1939, he was hired by President Franklin D. Roosevelt to be an archivist at Roosevelt's library in Hyde Park. After the involvement of the United States in World War II in 1941, he was called to Washington to work with the Office of Strategic Services (OSS) to study classified slavic materials and intelligence. Upon the conclusion of the war in 1945, he joined the faculty at Duke and spent the rest of his career there.
In 1954 he received a Guggenheim Fellowship in Russian History, and in 1966 was designated a James B. Duke Professor of history.
In his personal life, he married Edna Sutter on September 21, 1925 in Buffalo, New York. They had two children, Anne Curtiss Fong, and John Sutter Curtiss. After his retirement from Duke University, Curtiss became involved with a number of local Durham organizations, including the Durham County Public Library, the Kiwanis Club, and the Lebanon Volunteer Fire Department. He was also heavily involved in collecting and preserving his family's history and genealogical materials.
Upon the death of his wife in Durham, North Carolina on May 22nd, 1981, Curtiss moved to Honolulu, Hawaii to live with his daughter and her family until his death on December 27th, 1983.
New York (State) -- Genealogy; Connecticut -- Genealogy; Historians -- Correspondence; Genealogies; Curtiss, John Shelton; Curtiss, Harlowe Clarke; Curtiss, Edna Sutter; Duke University--Faculty; Durham County (N.C.). Library; Sutter family; Curtiss family
- Professional Papers, 1957-1981; 1
  - Article: Russian Army Under Nicholas I, 1976-1979 (Box 1)
  - Book Reviews, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Charles E. Walker, Microfilm Loan, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Columbia University Press- Church and State in Russia, 1968-1980 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Press, Russian Army Royalties, 1974-1978 (Box 1)
  - Illustrations, Russia's Crimean War, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Liberalism in the Russian Church, Undated (Box 1)
  - Reccomendations, 1977-1980 (Box 1)
  - Reviews, 1973-1980 (Box 1)
  - Russia's Crimean War Comments, 1976-1980 (Box 1)
  - Russia's Crimean War, Publication Matters, 1973-1980 (Box 1)
  - Russia's Crimean War, Review Bestuzhev-Lada, 1979-1981 (Box 1)
  - Russian History in the United States (Article Manuscript), 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Russian Social History to 1917, Undated (Box 1)
  - Van Nostrand, 1963-1968 (Box 1)
  - Vita and Publication Record, 1957-1967 (Box 1)
- Personal Papers, 1913-1981; 2
  - ADA Collection, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Adaptation Study, Center for the Study of Aging, 1970-1976 (Box 1)
  - Anne C. Fong, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - Anne C. Fong, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Anne C. Fong, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Anne C. Fong, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Anne's Financial Plans, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Becky Heron, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Bernard Oppel, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Bruce W. Menning, 1970-1977 (Box 1)
  - Carl Stewart Campaign, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Common Cause NC, 1975-1979 (Box 1)
  - Carrington Community Education Center, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Christmas, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Curtiss Autobiography, circa 1979 (Box 1)
  - David R. Jones, 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Distribution of Furniture, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Don Gillin, 1970-1979 (Box 1)
  - Durham County Library, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Durham Voters Alliance, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Elizabeth, 1977-1979 (Box 1)
  - Eno River, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Ethel Mann Curtiss Reminiscences, 1939 (Box 1)
  - Frederick Krantz, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Friends of the Durham County Library, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Garden File, 1965-1971 (Box 1)
  - Gordon Cook, 1972-1977 (Box 1)
  - General File (Personal), 1979 (Box 1)
  - General File (Personal), 1978 (Box 1)
  - General File (Personal), 1977 (Box 1)
  - General File (Personal), 1976 (Box 1)
  - General File (Personal), 1975 (Box 1)
  - General File (Personal), 1974 (Box 1)
  - General File (Personal), 1973 (Box 1)
  - General File (Personal), 1972 (Box 1)
  - General File (Personal), 1971 (Box 1)
  - General File (Personal), 1970 (Box 1)
  - General File (Personal), 1969 (Box 1)
  - Johnny and Lynne, Undated (Box 1)
  - Kiwanis Club, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - League of Women Voters, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Lebanon Volunteer Fire Department Inc., 1972-1977 (Box 1)
  - Letters Concerning Estate Settlements, Family Life`, 1924-1946 (Box 1)
  - Letters to Congress, 1974-1980 (Box 1)
  - McNeill Smith, 1976-1978 (Box 1)
  - NC Legislators, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Pat Dunn, 1972-1980 (Box 1)
  - Curtiss Papers - Personal Archive, 1948-1980 (Box 1)
  - Personal and Family Letters, 1913-1981 (Box 1)
  - Princeton Class of 1921, 1954-1980 (Box 2)
  - Ruritan, 1974-1980 (Box 2)
  - Ruritan Certificate of Appreciation, 1981 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Ruritan, Orkin, 1969-1979 (Box 2)
  - Senator George McGovern, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Taxation with Representation, 1973-1977 (Box 2)
  - Terry Sanford, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Texas Land Sale, 1953-1973 (Box 2)
  - Texas Land Titles, 1970-1980 (Box 2)
  - Texas Property Mineral Rights, 1973-1975 (Box 2)
  - Triangle J Council of Governments, 1975-1977 (Box 2)
  - United Fund, 1977 (Box 2)
- Family History, Genealogy, 1796-1980; 3
  - Alex Curtiss Photograph, Undated (Box 2)
  - Baptismal Certificates, Judson House Photograph, 1862-1904 and Undated (Box 2)
  - Baptismal Font Gift, H.C. Curtiss, 1909 March 2 (Box 2)
  - Birthplace, 1904 (Box 2)
  - Buffalo, City of; Family History, 1845-1968 (Box 2)
  - Charles Curtiss Memoriam Text, Third National Bank Meeting Minutes, 1893 October 2 (Box 2)
  - Christmas Card, 1908 (Box 2)
  - Christmas Photograph, 1916 (Box 2)
  - Curtiss Children, 1905 (Box 2)
  - Curtiss Family Letters, 1855-1910 (Box 2)
  - Curtiss House, Undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1832-1851 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1850 February 4 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1900-1901 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Undated, circa 1870-1900 (Box 2)
  - Dayton House, Undated, circa 1890-1920 (Box 2)
  - Decree of Excommunication, Kaminski, 1898 October 15 (Box 2)
  - Family Genealogy from 839, Undated (Box 2)
  - Family Correspondence, 1936-1981 (Box 2)
  - Family Correspondence, 1937-1956 (Box 2)
  - Family History, Ethel Curtiss, 1939 July (Box 3)
  - First Letter from Esther, 1901 July 6 (Box 3)
  - Genealogy, Undated (Box 3)
  - Genealogy, 1914-1980 (Box 3)
  - Genealogy and Letter, 1899 November 11 (Box 3)
  - Genealogical Information, Undated (Box 3)
  - Genealogical Information, Undated (Box 3)
  - Genealogical Investigation, 1901 (Box 3)
  - Genealogical Materials, Undated (Box 3)
  - Genealogical Papers, Undated (Box 3)
  - Harlow Curtiss Death, Resolution, Articles, 1933 (Box 3)
  - Harlow Curtiss Letter, 1899 (Box 3)
  - H.C. Curtiss, circa 1860 (Box 3)
  - Inventory of Early Curtiss Documents, Correspondence, 1900, Undated (Box 3)
  - John C. Curtiss in his Teens, Undated (Box 3)
  - Letter, 1901 July 8 (Box 3)
  - Letter from Amelia Curtiss to Fanny Foster, 1858 December 23 (Box 3)
  - Letter to C.G. Curtiss' Children, 1885 April 10 (Box 3)
  - Letter Fragment, 1882 (Box 3)
  - Letter from H. C. Curtiss' Grandmother, 1840 January 15 (Box 3)
  - Letter to H. C. Curtiss from James Shepard, 1901 May 27 (Box 3)
  - Letter to H.C. Curtiss from his Mother, 1880 November 22 (Box 3)
  - Letter from H.C. Curtiss' Mother to "Aunt Anne", 1851 April 19 (Box 3)
  - Letter to Harlow Curtiss, 1900 (Box 3)
  - Letter from Lyman Curtiss to his Children, 1840 February 8 (Box 3)
  - Letters from Relatives (in Poland and Germany) of Edna Curtiss, 1932-1968 (Box 3)
  - Letters from Relatives (in Poland and Germany) of Edna Curtiss, 1937-1952 (Box 3)
  - Lyman L. Curtiss Letter, 1839 November 29 (Box 3)
  - Manuscript Biography Ezekial Curtiss, undated (Box 3)
  - Memorandum, undated (Box 3)
  - Marriage Certificate, 1896 (Box 3)
  - Moscow Trip, 1955 September (Box 3)
  - Nelson Letter from the Front, 1918 October 3-10 (Box 3)
  - Obituary, William Moseley, 1896 (Box 3)
  - Poems, Undated (Box 3)
  - Post Card, 1918 (Box 3)
  - Photographic Portrait of Great-Grandfather, Undated (Box 3)
  - Photograph, circa 1880-1910 (Box 3)
  - Photographs, circa 1901-1922 and Undated (Box 3)
  - Photographs of John Curtiss, 1921-1922 (Box 3)
  - Photograph Reproductions, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Photograph, Stiles Judson Curtiss, circa 1923 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Photographs, Stiles Judson Curtiss, undated (Box 3)
  - Postcards, 1948-1958 and undated (Box 3)
  - Princeton Term Report John Curtiss, Financial Documents, 1900-1920 (Box 3)
  - Religious Commentary, undated, circa 19th century (Box 3)
  - Religious Materials, 1841 April 5 (Box 3)
  - Rowing Team, Matthew Darbyshire Mann, circa 1920s and Undated (Box 3)
  - State Department Papers, Genealogical Information, 1886 and Undated (Box 3)
  - Stratford Connecticut Photographs, Letter Fragments, 1815 and Undated (Box 3)
  - Stratford Connecticut Post Cards, 1906 and Undated (Box 3)
  - Trinity College Trustee Election; Society of Colonial Wars, State of New York; Genealogical Materials, 1900-1907 (Box 3)
  - University of Buffalo, School of Medicine, 1938 December 12 (Box 3)
  - Vacation Photographs, circa 1880-1930 (Box 3)
  - Verdun Memorium, 1920 (Box 3)
  - Withdrawal Recipt, Undated (Box 3)
  - Writ for Damages, 1796 (Box 3)
  - 1712 Letter Ephraim Stiles, [Hand Copy Facsimile], Undated (Box 3)
  - Ford Genealogy, Being an Account of Some of the Fords Who were Early Settlers in New England, 1916 (Box 4)
  - Sketches of Church Life in Colonial Connecticut, 1902 (Box 4)
  - The Quarto-Millenial Anniversary of the Congregational Church of Stratford Connecticut, 1899 September 5 (Box 4)
  - The Complete Works of Turgenev Vol. II, 1921 (Box 5)
  - The Complete Works of Turgenev Vol. III, 1921 (Box 6)
  - The Complete Works of Turgenev Vol. IV, 1921 (Box 7)
  - The Cor Family in America - A History and Genealogy of the Older Branches of the Family from the Appearance of its first Representatives in the Country in 1610. Including the Cock-Cocks-Cox Genealogy of Long Island by Reverend Henry Miller Cor and George William Cox, 1912 (Box 8)
  - Genealogical and Family History of Western New York - A Record of the Achievments of her People in the Making of a Commonwealth and the Building of a Nation Vol. I by William Richard Cutter, 1912 (Box 9)
  - Genealogical and Family History of Western New York - A Record of the Achievments of her People in the Making of a Commonwealth and the Building of a Nation Vol. II by William Richard Cutter, 1912 (Box 10)
  - Genealogical and Family History of Western New York - A Record of the Achievments of her People in the Making of a Commonwealth and the Building of a Nation Vol. III by William Richard Cutter, 1912 (Box 11)
  - Genealogy and History of the Curtiss Family of Stratford Connecticut and Decedents in America from 1631 to 1901 Vol. I by Edwin Curtiss (Box 12)
  - Genealogy and History of the Curtiss Family of Stratford Connecticut and Decedents in America from 1631 to 1901 Vol. II by Edwin Curtiss (Box 13)
  - History of Stratford and Bridgeport Connecticut Pt. 1 by Samuel Orcutt, 1886 (Box 14)
  - History of Stratford and Bridgeport Connecticut Pt. 2 by Samuel Orcutt, 1886 (Box 15)
  - A History of the Dorcester Pope Family 1634-1888 with Sketches of other Popes in England and America, and Notes Upon Several Intermarrying Families by Charles Henry Pope (Box 16)
  - Homewood - Ridgeway Ontario - Guestbook, 1896-1920 (Box 17)
  - Pioneers of Utica: Being Sketches of its Inhabitants and Institutions, with the Civil History of the Place, from the Earliest Settlement to the Year 1825 - the era of the Opening of the Erie Canal by M.M. Bragg, 1877 (Box 18)
  - Reunion of the Decendents of Daniel Shelton in Birmingham Connecticut, June 14th 1877, 1877 June 14 (Box 19)
  - Scrapbook - Ethel Curtiss, 1897-1937 (Box 20)
  - State Legislature Bill Draft, Niagara River, Lewiston, NY, 1826 Apr. (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Transactions of the Medical Society of the State of New York, 1858 (Box 21)